now generally speaking when you think
about how all of this was right you have
information and you have rules and out
of back door conclusion so we sort of
have this general pan is . and that
makes sued
ok you think about what you've done and
then make sure I space what computers
actually really as kind of place you can
we'll get started this and just out of
that girl's blood to the up is what I
mean right I got away
let me give you a name for this event
for dial to the decision
ok it's called for would change because
as Mike going four dollars
decision-making orgy
now you may call the system start from a
decision and go back to what . yeah that
might seem a bit backwards to you which
is why it's called back machine but
actually as you'll see bit as humans we
both of these on a regular basis all the
time my questions trying to fly this
right
sometimes once useful sometimes the
others and some have the combination of
the time it's like to be back with other
side back to change
ok back to change now ya series i want
to make some kind of decision right so i
think i was talking about the weather
before and whether i should
next course in person i get up in the
morning and i'll tell you a lot about
two pieces of clothing now that question
should i wear jumpline extra doctor
today right
that's the decision right so actually my
starting point for starting point
he's a decision and I wanted to know
whether I should do it or not
what kind of variable they're on a
mission accomplished that
so in that case I've actually begun here
on this side and back with Shane right
so now that I've started with my
decision
I need to see sure you're not so now i'm
going to go search for some garlic that
relates the data see my phone and check
it out right or you know why fight them
something like that so I look at the
window optimize the air coming through
for so you see started this decision key
guys what . i should look at that except
so in some ways you might think this is
a convergent fresh right I'm sort of god
goal in mind for drilling towards that
once i'm going up information then I
don't need to look at anything else I
can make packaging is flourishing
well as it flies you just stop with the
decision you're gonna make you might
have no idea what decision you're going
to instead you just stop in the dog will
you write gather is much daughters can
get everything that you don't know when
it's gonna be really not just grab once
you've got all of that
try your best combine everything you got
here like and see all right what does
this lead to what decisions or decisions
mike is ladyboy now we've clearly that
wasn't such a good example for for
change that one back to changing
situations on the decision
look for some garlic but just yesterday
I have to make a decision which was for
change which was no should I shoes to be
the three people to get points for best
and fairest after sport
ok so if you don't know the system
best-and-fairest regrets for you
actually one person who gets the award
actually three and they get three points
two points was okay and at the end of
the season out of everyone . and then
you get rolled this very here's the
thing
oh I have I have 24 people like to teach
actually I don't get cool people who
played games with it because
unfortunately i didn't Jesus or also be
intimidated the other to do tell
so here so i just 12 players to choose
from ok so we go and look at my list
right now if i want to back with changes
it would look something like this
we're playing on the one who this person
get points for best affairs so there's
my decision that right and then figure
out okay what daughter relates to that
so then I I think back to the game on
this ball their school and so on ok so
then I don't think it now that I've got
pushed out can make a decision that yes
it might be just like the one where you
can start to see why this is a problem
an approach to this particular problem
right because having started this
decision okay I'm gonna do it again
yeah that's a very time to process this
so instead i'm going to start with the
dark
I'm going down going back to the game
first rather than any particular
decision and referred ok this is what
happened is what's to that this was
unusual unusual and authenticated based
on all of that . i'm going to make a
decision that this will be a person who
I think stood out the most and they're
going to get 31 only so because it
begins with the dollar
this is often called a planted driven
it's often what works best when you
simply turned out which choices to
actually stop ask what you can do is
look at the situation and well what do
we know
and therefore decisions can be made on
the basis of its often also very helpful
we're not just one you have to shoot
you're actually going to end up with a
few different included right business in
my knowledge base my rules might be
things like if someone scores right well
i would only want me to have three kids
and it's okay they're gonna be my top
contenders for best and fairest right so
there's a rule that's fired that's being
late with relevant right and then I have
a little bit of rules and put that all
together and see who are my top three so
yeah it's it's a different way of life
difference between