i'm going to talk about constraint
satisfaction problems for example so you
have a map of Australia here and the
task is to color each region is a red
green or blue and no adjacent region can
have the same color that is those are
constraints and that's a constraint
satisfaction problem so constraint
satisfaction problem we've seen so far
if you've been following the videos
other algorithms that we evaluate states
with heuristics in a goal right I
constraint satisfaction problem is a
factor of representation of a state
where you have a set of variables with a
value the idea that you have constraints
now that allows for more efficient
algorithms and we want to find is any
solution now there isn't enough to mom
there isn't there's a solution
ok and either they have a solution or
they don't
ok the way of constraint satisfaction
problems we're going to see now there's
another variant of constraint
satisfaction problems in which there is
an ideal solution but if it cannot be
found there's you know a second best
we're going to talk a little bit about
that in future slides
well the constraint satisfaction problem
have a formulation usually there's a set
of variables a set of domains for each
variable and a set of constraints that
my involve these variables
ok so i'll explain a little bit what
each one of these is right so X is set
of variables that goes from x 1 to x and
so all the variables in your program in
your problem
these the set of domain so basically for
each of these variables
what are the possible values they can
take ok so there's a domain so I for
each X sub I ok and then there's a set
of constraint which is basically the
scope what what are the variables
involved what's the scope involved in
what is going to be the relationship
between those variables
ok usually we won't do the notation
where we put scope common relationship
so much we'll just put some constraints
but we'll start with
australia problem the idea is to color
each region of Australia with a
different color and no adjacent regions
should have the same color and you only
can choose between red green or blue
another way of looking at this program
this problem is to put it as a graph
where you have saw the southern
Australia here in southern Australia is
connected to Western Australia the
northern territories queensland new
south wales and victoria scientists
money is unconnected to any of these
right and then perhaps by looking at is
a tree we can use looking at the graph
we can use some of our search problems
to help us guide through this but let's
look at the formulation you have the
variables the variables are the
different states southern Australia New
South Wales Northern Territory western
australia queensland Victoria and I
forgot test mania right there but let's
let's think that testimony is is now
there it should actually appear anytime
so these are the these are the variables
now you see that there is also the
domain whoops all right there's this
mania
ok so then there's also the domains so
for each of these so for example for
southern Australia the choices are red
blue or green these are the values that
each one of these can take now in this
problem each variable can actually take
the same colors initially right so so so
that's the domain of the of the
variables
ok now the constraints
well the scope is for every for all
variables
ok XO x such that x sub J is touching
for all pairs of variables xixj such
that they're touching each other
ok that's the scope
the constraint is the color of the one
should be different than the color of
the other ok so this is a way of
describing a set of constraints
ok let's look at another problem for
example scheduling classes
okay how do we formulate provide
scheduling classes in terms of variables
variables domains and constraints
well one way of doing it is for example
if you take these are the computer
science classes these each class is a
variable and then the domain is the
classes the times the days and times
which these classes can actually happen
right so for example first-years 235 can
be monday at 9am monday at 11am monday
$MONTH $DAY 1pm and so on and so forth
right so these are days in which class
can happen and we can formulate the
following constraint for all IJ for all
IJ if the variable in the classes of
xixj our core requisites then the times
must be different if they're not
correctness it's well then they can
happen at the same time that can be one
way of formulating this problem now
there's another concept called the old
if that might help us develop
constraints so for example we have sued
aku here in which this space has to be
different than this base has to be
different than this place and so on and
so forth right well instead of putting
many many constraints instead of putting
like I don't know how many many
constraints we can do all diff and we
can do there's an old if for the columns
that's 90 tips for the columns then
there's an altar for the road saying all
the numbers here must be different right
so that there's nine all dates for the
rose and then there's also an all diff
for each square
ok so within a square each of these
variables which is sliding the Sudoku
puzzle each of the variables should be
all different right so there's nine in
the squares and that gives us a total of
twenty-seven called dibs is a lot less
than say the simpler way to put this is
81 pairs you know difference but then
it's a lot more if you have to consider
this we're not only for each square for
each square you have you have a 80
possibility so there's a lot of
constraints in here if you start
computing them
okay all right now there's other kinds
of puzzles the usually they called the
script automatic puzzles where the
problem is like this so they say 2+2 is
4 and all these letters stand for a
number
ok so one can think of the constraints
as follows
ftu wro they're all different all the
unique letters here are all different
they're all different numbers and then
also we know that Oh plus 0 is our right
Oh bless always are but what if Oh is
safe for example 7 7 plus 7 is 14 so our
would be four and and the one gets
carried over here right
so instead we can say that Oh plus 0 is
r + 10 times the carry
ok so hopeless always r + 10 times for
Kerry of the tents right so if oh we're
to be seven we have 77 is 4 plus 10 x 10
x 1
right because the carrier is one
r is for + 10 times one that's 14 right
so one can say that
Oh bless always r + 10 times the carry
in the same way one can say that W and
up w $OPERAND plus w + this Carrie is
you write and then but perhaps there's a
carried to this side as well what if WWE
r 7 so 7 plus 7 is 14 plus the one
that's 15 that's us five and there's a
carry but this Carrie is now in the
hundreds and the same things gonna
happen with T&O so the constraints to
stand like this
oh + 0 must be r + 10 times the carry
now that carry if press it right plus w
$OPERAND plus w so I'm looking at this
home right now
ok w $OPERAND plus w must be u + 10
times the carry of 100 in the same way
in the same way we can see that we can
see that then the next the next time
around we're going to have for the teeth
right so let's look at the teeth now
we're looking at this column here right
t plus t plus the current the carry of
the hundred so the second carry right
plus the carried the hundreds must be 0
so the care of the hundreds plus t plus
t must be equal to 0 plus 10 times the
carrier of the thousands which basically
I this numbers they don't know much
except which place that carries on and
then F must be the carrier of the
thousands because there's no letters
about ok that's how we could specify the
constraints here i'm not doing it in the
form of skull
skull color relationships right I'm not
doing like that i'm just doing the
relationships and the scope is the
variables involved here right so for
example the scope of of this constraint
would be the values
oh and are right and then I introduce
this c10 and from now on because trains
i'm going to just put the constraints
like this another way of representing
this is for example in a tree what this
square is the old if these are all
different and then F&T you know they
added together and they go into another
constraint which is they together have
c3 they together create another variable
to which they're just that that is
involved in this constraint TR for
example of ya 70r are involved there u
and w right are involved right you and
WR involved you and WR involved in this
constraint uw-w are involved and they
also involves see of 100 and CEO of
tents and they also loves the second
carry and the first carry the first
carries you have 10 carries your 100
right so this basically has a graph that
tells you which variables are involved
this is CEO of 100 this is I do note
that I denoted these I'm sorry this sea
of 10 cf10 this is sea of 100 also
called it and this is C or 1000 it's the
same they're the same variables
ok so this is another way of writing of
specifying a constraint satisfaction
problem that goes like that now
constraint satisfaction problems there's
there's a kind of constraints different
kinds of constraints of the unity
constraints involved a single variable
so for example the colors in the
Australian upright so southern what
southern Australia cannot be green or
southern Australia cannot be purple
because the colors are green blue and
red a binary involve
superior variable so for example
southern Australia cannot be of the same
color the same assignment as Western
Australia for example right and there
might be a higher order which involved
three or more which is which are the
ones that we just saw in the crypt
automatic puzzle
well we can search if we have if we have
a way of searching this right we can we
can do a death limited search with a
constraint satisfaction constraint
satisfaction problem with n variables
ok so for example in the Australian we
have on we have six variables for the
six states and each state has a domain
size d in the the work of the Australian
puzzle this is three right
the branching factor of the top is going
to be n times d because all assignments
are possible for all variables right now
the next level you can have one less
assignment you know times the domain
size right because you assign the first
one and then the rest can only have one
less assignment right and in the end you
end up with n factorial times d2 the end
leaves in this tree
ok now only due to the end possible
assignments are completed assignments
right so this clearly is clearly a
search problem that we have to optimize
somehow so one way of doing this is the
backtracking and noting the following
the variable assignments are commutative
so if i say Western Australia's red and
that implies the Northern Territory
screen this is the same as in northern
note the church's green implies that
Western Australia is right there
commutative so this factorial is is
reduced now right if we only consider
one combination right we're going to try
to consider assignment to a single
variable pitch note and then what
happens is that if we find an
inconsistent or an illegal value on an
assignment will backtrack ok
this can solve the endpoints for an
approximately 25 from our values it
quite so it will see that in a bit
alright so backtracking the algorithm
for backtracking is basically a depth
first visit on the assignments but
here's the the the the the important
lines if the value is consistent with
the assignment there we add this value
to the assignment
ok then we do all possible inferences in
our tree because for example if we have
the australia in australia of fossil
here right and we assign some color here
and some color here some color here we
already we can infer what the color
should be here right where we assigned
two colors because there's only three
colors two colors we can already affair
what this color is going to be so we
don't need to actually make it part of
the assignment right we just do all the
possible inferences and then we continue
with the next variable which would be
this one to assign ok that's the idea of
of this that's that's one important
point of this of this tree visiting a we
do the inferences if we encounter that
the inference are going to lead to a
failure i mean if if the influences of
do not lead to failure
we're going to add all the assignments
that we've referred to the global
assignments
okay and then we will just recursively
call this function now at the end once
all the assignments are done if the
result is not a failure then return that
result now if this condition fails for
this condition fails or value is not
consistent with the assignment right
then other values are going to be tried
once all the values are tried and
nothing is consistent what happens is
you're going to remove that value right
we're going to remove that value and
inferences from the assignment and we're
going to start you know we're gonna
start with the next one so on and so
forth evolves fails then we'll return
failure no solutions found for example
let's start with this map right that the
map of Australia and we have all of our
choices here right we have read for
Western Australian let's start with
Western with Western Australia first
ok that's the state and we're looking at
right now we have this through possible
assignments let's look at this branch
now
ok now we're gonna not only Western
Australia but now we're going to assign
the northern territories collar now so
far so good
let's continue with the assigned
possible assignments for this one so
then we want to assign queensland the
collar right here's here's an
interesting
here's an interesting thing yeah we can
send breslin a color right red or blue
and if we were to follow this one
forward to make inferences here right
it will infer something that's illegal
there's no color that can go here right
so once the inferences are made after we
assign this color we will never pursue
this branch
ok we'll only pursue this one and if we
find something it was it would find
something that's illegal again we'll
backtrack and you know not pursue this
will pursue others
ok however there are many ways in which
this can be optimized for example when
we're at this tab right it might be
advisable to assign the color for the
southern Australia province
ok maybe useful to sign this one because
this one is the one that's going to get
us more bent for the back if this is say
cannot be green cannot be read
there's only one color for this guy
where there's two colors for the state
right there's this one can be can be in
the case that is green
this one can be blue or it can be read
but this one has only one possible
assignment
perhaps you want to just sign this one
and then continue that way the trees
gonna is gonna do a lot less backtracks
in the future so as I can I just
illustrate it is really important to
know how to choose the next variable
that you're going to test 111 way of
looking at this is to choose what's
going to become the the minimum
remaining value so let's look at a
variable or mrv let's look at this is a
heuristic that it's going to look at the
value with the fewest legal values in
this case right
southern Australia is the one with the
fewest legal values at this step is it
can only be blue right so there's one
big value where this one has to legal
values
that's the minimum remaining values it's
it's it really improves the search a lot
there's degree here mystics basically
pick the variable that's involved in
most constraints because if you pick
that variable you already reduced the
this the domains on the other variables
right so if I pick again degree here is
similar
this one is the one that's involved with
more states here because almost all
states but menya touches southern
Australia so maybe I want to pick this
value first actually I could start
instead of starting with Western
Australia or the I could have started
with immediately start coloring this
south australia right away so then i
have less choices for these others and
the tree might be smaller and then
there's another one that looks ahead
another heuristic that is used it's the
least constraining value the idea here
is to look
Oh what are the ones that are going to
have the most slack in terms of values
that I can assign to them right and then
the things that this looks ahead a
little bit and will prefer that the
trees that generate more flexibility for
the future now we can always have
check for constraint consistency and we
can do this is called inference so we
always whatever assignment we do we try
to infer whether it's gonna weather it
conflicts with something else and one
algorithm to do this is the our
consistency 3 this is ac3 this is an
algorithm from the seventies
it's called three because of the paper
that was published this was the third
algorithm and it is you can look for
this in wikipedia it makes a lot of
sense it has a stack with pairs of of of
link note so as soon as soon as I
constraint satisfaction problem is
represented as a graph
ok then we want to find the art of the
consistency between these RX there's
another way of improving the tree
exploration and that's called forward
checking and this really saves a lot of
time and forward checking what it does
is basically it looks at each variable X
in the constraint satisfaction problem
and for each variable for each and
assign variable ok why that it's
connected to the to the variable that
I'm exciting right now and for each of
the values d in the domain of that
variable i will see it d is inconsistent
with the value that I have assigned x
then I'll take that that value from the
domain and then I'll do this for every
very well every time we do an assignment
i'll pass the constraint satisfaction
problem with the assignments as a
forward checking i will check and reduce
the domain of the variables that would
be in conflict and i'll return the new
CSP with the modified domains for
example let's say we have the Australian
map right so the Westralian northern
territory queensland new south wales
victoria southern Australia and Tasmania
the domain for all of this is red green
or blue at this point but now let's
assign read to Western Australia so
after Western Australia's read here
right then the northern traders can only
be green or blue
queensland can only be red green or blue
the north north of New South Wales can
be a red green or blue Victoria regular
blue now South Australia can be only
green blue and the just mean it can be
any color so then we assigned for
example queensland green ok
queensland green now the northern
territories can only be blue new south
wales only red and blue and South
Australian only blue then we'll assign
Victoria blue right so one of these so
I'm keeping assignments here that I know
what are all the possible assignments so
i don't have to explore them all right
so then I think Victoria blue for
example here right and so on and so
forth but we realize one thing here
there's no possible domain here in South
Australia this is failure if before
checking finds no potential domain no
domain variables in one of no domain
values for one of the variables
okay then it's a failure right and then
if it returns failure algorithm should
backtrack as well
now one last algorithm in constraint
satisfaction problems one less
consideration is that we can change
variables using heuristics for one
heuristic that is very useful is the one
of minimum conflicts we want to check
which assignments which values of
assignments produce the minimum amount
of conflicts
ok so in this in this way we can check
this for a number of steps before giving
up
okay otherwise we might be doing this
for for a while and the idea here is
that we will look at variables will look
at current assignments
ok to see if there a solution for the
constraint satisfaction problem if if
they are the assignments solution then
return it
if not we're going to create a variable
that is going to be a randomly chosen
conflicted variable in csb we're going
to look for a conflicted variable in
this assignment
ok and for this value we're going to
pick we're gonna pick we're going to
look at that variable and we're going to
pick the value that minimizes conflicts
and we'll put that in current and then
we're going to do this for however many
steps right and at some point current
will be the solution if not then we'll
return failure but just doing this
algorithm improves a lot of things so as
an example here we have the Queen's
problem right and these are the number
of conflicts that i will have if i move
the Queen at each one of these tips so
of course i want to move it to one of
the ones right randomly i love it to
this one
now there's a conflict with this Queen
this Queen has to move to the point of
minimum conflict and here's 20
I this this here the conflict 20 and I
move it there so by looking by doing
backtracking and loading at the minimum
number of conflicts to pick the next
note and also doing forward checking
your algorithms can be improved a lot
for example for the in-between problems
doing a lot of and bring problems for n
I believe a tail end till end as a 100 i
think look at look at what the
algorithms reported here so just using
backtracking ok we're going to do that
the entrance by the way I'm sorry then
quinces to queens all the way until 15
so find the solution for all those
problems right with backtracking over
40,000 thousand right so over 40 million
iterations ok and it could not find the
solution that's why it's inbred using
former checking for the same problem
again
it gave over 40 million iterations
without finding the solution now using
the minimal conflict
it was only 4,000 iterations
found the solution to all in queens
parcels from two queens to 2050 queens
now the same problem that we looked at
this electric with Australia has been
proven there with the united states
states the idea here for the for the
united states of america is with four
colors can we color all states of the
united states of america with four
colors such that no adjacent state has
the same color backtracking alone 2 1
million iterations and it didn't find a
solution return failure for checking
though selecting with forward checking
juices gives the solution 2000 relations
and if you use the minimal conflicts
algorithm it gives you a solution 64
iteration notice there's no connects to
this just 64 durations and there's a
very famous problem the zebra problem
ok in which the the zebra problem goes
goes a little bit like this try to solve
this problem there are five houses the
Englishman lives on the Red House the
Spaniard owns the dog coffee strong on
the greenhouse the Ukrainian drinks tea
and so on and so forth they give you
five houses they give you some
nationalities of the people that are
there you know that the five house they
have some people from five different
nationalities they're painted in
different colors people smoke five
different brands of cigarettes and they
drink different things and they have
different pets so they tell you a little
bit about each Hauser each nationality
or each pad or each habit and you have
to figure out where the zebra lives and
where people go to drink water
well with backtracking this can be
solved in about 4 million iterations for
checking 35,000 and with minimal
conflicts only 2,000 so these algorithms
do improve on each other and build upon
the other algorithms that we've that
we've looked in other videos