morning class sorry I can't be there
this morning
arm but it's ok we'll just do this over
video and today we're going to pick up
where we left off on friday we are in
unit 3 talking about eliminating
possibilities to solve problems
today's problems are all going to be
very similar the same type of problems
all day long and they're called crypt
arithmetic problems and they're not
exactly easy
ok they might not come easy to you at
first but I think with a little bit of
practice you'll understand them and
you'll get them and you'll do perfectly
fine arm after all things that are
worthwhile are difficult
so if they were all easy problems this
class will be very fun but the whole
point is to challenge you and and push
you and I think that these problems
today will will help push you armed
I'm going to go through a few examples
with you today
if at any time in the video though you
want to try the problem without hearing
the answer
you can pause the video try and work the
problem out in your notes and see how
you do and then play the video to see if
you got the same thing as me so that's
always a good strategy when you're
watching these videos to practice before
you hear the answer and then go ahead
and play it and see if you got the same
answers me
all right let's get started with the
first problem here the first problem is
called life on the farm and this is how
it goes
a meal and all have live on a farm with
their father Gordon one day email asked
his father dad what happened to that cat
we used to have all over heard this and
said yeah and we used to have a horse to
Gordon replied that Tomcat and that old
nag were no use
I traded them for our new goat email
said hey that sounds like a good script
arithmetic problem
come on all of let's see if we can solve
it they wrote down tom
Plus nag equals goat each letter stands
for a different digits 0 through 9 no 2
letters stand for the same digit
determine which digit each letter
represents
all right and that's kind of a lot of
language there but let's go to the next
slide and I kind of laid out what this
problem
looks like all right I apologize for my
sloppy handwriting but this is what the
problem looks like we're trying to add
up
Tom plus nag to equal goat and if you
can see over on the right-hand side
each letter has a different possibility
for which number it could be for
instance
t it could be zero one two three four
five six seven eight or nine
notice that he cannot be 10 or 25 each
letter can only be one digit 0 through 9
the other thing that we need to know is
that if t were five for instance then M
could not be five because it
the number can't repeat ok also kind of
along the same lines if the tea and tom
was five then the tea and goat would
also have to be five
ok so we're trying to figure out what
each letter represents what number does
each letter represent all right so let's
walk through this i'm going to go kind
of slow on this first one here
let's walk through this step-by-step the
first letter that I know for sure is i
know that G has to be a one and let me
try and explain that here
I think that G has to be one the reason
why I think that G has to be one is the
biggest number that T could be would be
nine
ok that's the biggest number possible 40
and 50 is nine the biggest number that
end could possibly be would be 80 k & 9
+ 8
those are the biggest possible answers
that they could be in 9 + ape only adds
up to 17
so see how that g at the show then would
be a seven and I'd carry the war
one and the g would be a 1 see that
there's no way that she could be a three
for instance because there's no way that
T plus n could add up to 30 something
right the biggest that T plus n could
add up to a 17
so that's why I know that g must be one
and I don't know about
Oh or n or tea
I don't know about any of those yet arm
but I do know that g must be one
ok and if the g and goat is one than the
g and meg is also one so i'm going to
put a one there by that G over all my
letters over here
hopefully you can jot down something
like this on your notes because what i
want to do is I want to eliminate
possibilities so I know that g is 1 i'm
going to go ahead and circle the one
down there by G which means i can
eliminate the 0 in the 2 and the 3 and
the 4 and the 5 and the 6 and 7 and the
eight and the nine
the other thing that I can do is I can
eliminate the other letters i know that
a cannot be won I know that end cannot
be won em cannot be 10 cannot be 1 and T
cannot be won
ok so already now I've eliminated some
possibilities
alright the next thing that I'm looking
at as I look at this problem and this is
not easy
hey it's kind of difficult no doubt
about it but when i look at the this
Oh plus a equals a the oh and Tom the a
and nag and the a and go 0 plus a equals
a
okay or you know something
plus a equals a
alright so when I think about that I
think that
Oh must have to be 0 because 0 plus a
would equal a right 0 plus 4 is 40 plus
8 is 8 so i think that the 0 in
arm has to be a 0 and if that o is a0
than the Owen goat also has to be a zero
so i'm going to go ahead and fill those
in 20 so I'm my own up here i'm going to
circle the zero cross out the two three
four five six seven eight and nine
cross out the ont & M and N and a ok
I've eliminated some possibilities here
I know that the 0 is 0 the g is one
now let's look at this T plus n t plus n
t plus n has to equal 10
ok so there's only so many numbers that
can add up to ten one thing is 5 plus 5
equals 10
but if t is five then n can't be five so
i know that that's not the right answer
ok so at this point what you can do is
you can just kind of make some guesses
and try it and see if it works out
and if it doesn't work out then at least
you know that that's not the answer and
you can eliminate that possibility but
for me I know that 7 plus 3 equals 10
so i'm going to go ahead and try that
i'm going to try seven for my tea and
three for my end and if the tea and
Thomas seven then the tea and goat must
be seven
ok so i'm going to go ahead and circle
those ones over here i think t might be
seven so I'm going to eliminate the
other numbers that also means that m is
not seven and n is not seven and a is
not seven
I think that the n is 3 so I'm going to
circle 34 n cross out the other numbers
ok which means that m is not 3a is not
three
there we go
i'm going down to just a few
possibilities now all right let's look
at that
em up there that m m+ one has to equal 7
so that means that M must be six right
because six plus one equals seven so m
is six cross out the other possibilities
I know that a can't be six
ok excellent and so now the only letter
that i'm left with is a ok and when I
look at my possibilities for a a could
be 245 eight or nine
as long as I choose any of those numbers
I think this problem is going to work
out
so let's just choose i think five is a
lucky number so i'm going to choose 5
for a and if the day and nag is five and
the a and goat must be five guys on the
circle five cross out the other
possibilities
there we go I've got it
ok so now what I want to do is I just
want to double check my answer and make
sure that everything makes sense i'm
going to start over on the right
six plus one equals seven
that makes sense zero plus 5 equals 5
that makes sense and seven plus three
equals 10
that also makes sense so on this
particular problem
one possible solution is 706 + 350 1
equals 1057 ok and then this particular
problem there's more than one correct
answer you could have had a couple
different things but that's how you end
up with your answer
ok so let's try another problem
this next problem there's only one
possible answer so that makes it a
little bit trickier in some ways but in
some ways it also makes it a little bit
easier because you can eliminate more
possibilities
ok let's look at the next problem the
next problem is called the letter from
college and this is how it goes
the story goes that a young man away at
college needed some extra cash
he sent his mother this plea
he wanted her to send the amount
indicated by the following some send
plus more equals money
each letter stands for a different
digits 0 through 9 no 2 letters stand
for the same digit
how much money did the young man want
assume that there's a decimal point
between the end in the e because his
mother is probably not willing to send
10,000 or so dollars to her son on
request
alright so when I go to the next slide
of them up again I apologize for the
sloppy handwriting but on this is how it
what I've got of that sin
plus more equals money along the
right-hand side
I just listed all of the letters that
were in this problem
ok so there are one two three four five
six seven eight letters in this problem
each letter has 10 possibilities ok so
there's only so many possibilities a lot
of students get really really
overwhelmed when they're solving these
problems but remember that there's only
10 possibilities for each letter so if
you get stuck on a letter
the most you're going to have to try
it's 10 different possibilities which
you probably want to try 10 because i'm
sure you can eliminate some of those
possibilities from the start
ok but let's try not to get overwhelmed
let's try this problem the first letter
that we should look at is that em out in
front our money
ok because in the last problem we went
through in realize that M has only one
possible choice
m must be equal to 1 ok and we kind of
figured that out on the last problem so
m is equal to 1
I can eliminate some possibilities then
i know that s can be 1 & II can't be won
and the 0 ry
none of those numbers can be one ok and
if the am and money is one then the am
and more must be one
all right very good
next the next number that i personally
see is this
s i know that s plus 1 has to equal 10
or more because i need to carry this one
out here to the M and money
ok so s plus 1 has to equal 10 or more
well there's not you know s can't be 12
or 13 at the biggest number that s could
be as nine and nine plus 1 is 10 ok so
that's what it has to be s has to be 9
so 9 plus 1 is 10 let me get caught up
over here i know that s must be nine so
it's not a date it's not seven cents
it's by 4 30 to 40 and he's not nine
across all these possibilities out and
all this crossing all this stuff out it
may seem like a bit of a trouble but
when you get down towards the end of the
problem it will help you so much when
you when you've eliminated so many of
the possibilities
you only have one or two possibilities
left it will save you I promise
ok I also know that Oh must be 0 so it's
not two three four five six seven eight
or nine and also he's not 0 and 90
I can eliminate all of those
possibilities ok if the oh and money is
not our 20 excuse me
then the oh and more must be 0
ok so here we get to a funny situation
when we look at the E and send be plus 0
equals n and that doesn't make sense you
think he + 0 would equal e right but um
this is kind of a conundrum that we run
into
there's no way that he + 0 could equal
end because he plus 0 is e the only way
we could do that is if n plus R equals
something more than 10 and then we had
to carry a 1 up there above the ec that
ok then this might work out
ok so let's try a number for e and maybe
let's just try for let's try for
ok so I'm going to put a four in here
for e which means i need a for down here
and a 4 right there
ok and one plus four is five so the end
must be five
there we go now we're in another kind of
sticky situation here when we look at
the n plus R + + r has to equal 14 + +
RS equal 14 so 5 plus what equals 14
well you would think it would be nine
but the problem is that i've already
used in the nine so our can't be nine
so again when i figure out when i look
at this long enough as i know that our
must be eight and d + e must equal
something more than 10 because then i
have to carry a 1 up there above the 51
plus 5 and 6 6 plus 8 is 14 and then 1
plus 4 is 5 9 plus 1 is 10 so on and so
forth
all right which brings me to D and why
ok let me fill in some of this other
information here I know that
is for cross out cross out
I know that what else do I know our is
eight
okay i know that n is 5
and I think that's all I no no
alright so when i'm looking at this i'm
down to D and wine look at look at that
I've eliminated most of the
possibilities for d and why
here's the deal though is d + 4 has to
equal number bigger than 10 so
d the biggest number that d could be is
70 k + 7 + 4 is only 11
here's the problem though is that one
has already been used em is one
dang it not quite going to work out
ok so let's change some numbers here
see this is how L eliminating
possibilities works as you try some
possibilities and see if they work and
if they don't work then you try
something different
let's say that he isn't for let's say
that
e is five ok now we have seven plus 5 is
in 11
now that's 12
carry the 1 and can't be five anymore
let's say n is 6
here we go 1 plus 6 and 7 7 plus 8 is 15
so again this isn't for any more it's 15
carry the one
this e up here isn't for it must be a 5
1 plus 5 is 6 6 plus 0 is six and the
end up on sand is safe so it's a good
thing that the end I'm here and money
and six
so my gosh i think that that works
ok I think that 900
look sorry 9560 7 plus 1085 equals ten
thousand six hundred and fifty-two let's
just go through it one more time step by
step to make sure that it works 7 plus 5
is 12
carry the 1 1 plus 6 and 7 7 plus 8 is
carry the 1 1 plus 5 is 6 6 plus 0 is 69
plus 1 is 10 carry the one
excellent work so that's the solution to
this problem and it's not always going
to work out perfectly as we saw in this
example we found out that he could not
be four he had to be five
ok so let's try one more example in this
next example it's called here she comes
and it's here plus xi equals comes and
this problem is the same rules each
letter has to be a digit 0 through 9 no
2 letters can be the same digit same
rules that we've been playing all day
again this is a good chance for you to
pause the video and try this one out on
your own see if you can do it all on
your own and then watch the video and
see how I did
ok so I'm going to go to the next screen
again it's a good idea deposit and try
but i'm going to go ahead and solve this
thing ok
as I'm working here again the first
thing that I look at is the sea out
front I know that that C has to be a one
it can't be anything bigger than that he
has to be a one and eliminate some
possibilities here in just a moment
I
next then I look at that H and I don't
know that
h+ nothing has to equal 10 or bigger
hey so that's tough to do because the
biggest number H could be as a nine so
i'm going to go ahead and assume that H
must be 9 h is nine
all right and if the h and here is nine
then the h and she is also nine so we
know that I also know that i must be
carrying a one up here at the top
because 1 plus 9 equals 10
ok so that
Oh must be 0 so i know that i know all
must be 0
there we go it's coming along now ok now
I'm to the part where and i'm not
exactly sure where to go next so what I
need to do is I just need to try some
arm different numbers and see if they
work or not I had to do some trial and
error
sometimes it might work sometimes it
doesn't work ok so let's look at me
there's 1 2 3 4 e's so if i could figure
out yet but I could figure out the rest
of this problem
let's make a guess 4e ok last time he
was five
so let's try that again see if it works
again let's try
II that's 5k and already I can see that
that's not going to work because 5+5
would equal zero which means s would
have to be 0 and s can't be 0 because 0
is already 0 so that's not going to work
he can't be five so let me get my eraser
out
he's not five I know that ok so over on
my own chart over here I know that II
can't be five eliminate that possibility
ok let's try for maybe he is for that's
worth a try
ok four plus for then would be eight so
s might be eight means this s is eight
ok that looks good so far
then r + 9 has to equal 4 r plus 9 is
equal for that means our must be five is
five plus nine is 14 then I could carry
a 1 over here 1 plus 4 is 55 plus 8 is
the team carry the one which I needed
hey how it looks like we have a winner
here let's double check our answer
really quick go through to make sure
that it makes sense if he is 44 plus 4
is 8 s must be eight
ok then five plus nine is 14
carry the 1 1 plus 4 is 55 plus 8 is 13
carry the 1 1 plus 9 is 10 carry the one
so it looks like there's our answer i'm
going to go ahead and fill in my chart
here real quick
I found my answer
notice I didn't get my answer right on
the first try first I thought that he
was five
ok and so I did a little bit of math and
figured out that there's no way each
could have been five so i eliminated
five from the possibilities and I just
tried a different number
and don't be afraid to just do some
trial and error and try different
numbers out and see if you can come up
with the right one
all right it looks like I finished that
problem
the next slide is your homework problem
ok and this one you're going to have to
try all on your own if you want to work
with a partner to solve this one that's
okay you can work with a partner
the next one is called wow wow so cook
ok and it goes like this i dinnae was
having an argument with her roommate
Frankie about whether or not Frankie
could cook after arguing for a while
then they said wow so cook
Frankie who was a math teacher noticed
that donate what dinnae said might be a
crypt arithmetic problem
she sat down to work on it and then they
ended up cooking dinner
each letter in the crypt arithmetic
problem stands for a different digit
hint
k equals nine okay so they're giving UK
that's good i know that k equals nine
I also know that see got to equal one
so there's only three letters less a w +
0 and then s
those are the only three letters that
you have to figure out this problem
looks really really simple but it's a
little trickier than you think so you've
got to be very careful with it but you
only have three letters to figure out w
ons if you can solve this problem
you don't need to write any paragraphs
today just um solve this problem find
out what W equals what o is equal and
what s equals good luck I hope this
comes easy to you if you need to go back
and watch this video game that's no
problem
thank you and i will see you soon bye